Guide to the John Bowring Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John Bowring collection
1821-1871
GEN MSS 223
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.25
(1 box)
Chiefly letters from Bowring, many regarding unidentified works by his friends. Some letters are responses to invitations. Includes letter to Marc-Antoine Jullien about the Peace Society; letter to John Bowyer Nichols (editor of "Gentleman's Magazine") that includes a statement for publication about the destruction of the public library in Abo, Finland. Collection also includes manuscript regarding commercial relations between France and England, written for publication in "The Examiner", and two poems, one untitled and one entitled "Taxes."
Bowring, John, 1792-1872
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Material acquired from various sources.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of materials pertaining to John Bowring.
France -- Commerce -- Great Britain; Great Britain -- Commerce -- France; Poetry; Taxes; Bowring, John, 1792-1872; Jullien, Marc-Antoine, 1775-1848; Nichols, J. B. (John Bowyer), 1779-1863; Peace Society (London, England)
- Letters from John Bowring, 1792-1872, 1865 Sep 11
  - ALS to the Editor of the Athenaeum, Hong Kong, 1865 Sep 11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Tinker 370
  - ANS to W. Brochecon, [London?], 1831 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - ALS and ANS to Cerdier [unidentified], 1833 Aug 11, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - ALS to [Charles Augustin Coquerel], London, 1825 Aug 6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - ANS to Miss Crumpe, [London?], 1833 Feb 23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - ALS to [William Wallace Currie], London, 1826 Apr 18 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 2 ALS to William Hepworth Dixon, London and Claremont [?] Exeter, 1866 Jun 13, 1867 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Tinker 371, Tinker 372
  - ANS to William Jerden, [London?], 1831 Aug 3 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 5 ALS to Marc Antoine Jullien, London, 1821 Sep 23-[1830 Aug 4] (Box 1, Folder 9)
    1830 Aug 4 written inside a printed circular. Accompanied by a printed circular and a resolution (written in an unidentified hand and signed by Bowring) from the Peace Society, addressed to M. Jullien.
  - ALS to M. Moore (bookseller in Paris?), London, 1832 Feb 3 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - NS to [John Bowyer Nichols] the Editor of the Gentleman's Magazine, 1828 Jun 6 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Written on the second (blank) leaf of a printed circular, London.
  - ANS to Edwin Norris, London, 1853 Dec 15 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - ALS in French to Louis Philippe, London, 1821 Aug 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - ALS to Archibald Prentice, Exeter, 1829 Jul 28 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    On the same sheet: ALS from the author of the Catechism on the Corn Laws (Thomas Perronet Thompson), dated London, July 20, 1829.
  - ANS to Richard Ryan, London, 1824 Oct 29 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 2 form letters, with facsimile signatures of Sir John Bowring, addressed to C. A. Savage, London, 1824 Mar 22, Oct 12 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - ANS and ALS to C. R. Smith, London, 1842 May 18, May 5 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - ANS to the Rev. W[illiam] Tuckwell, Exeter, 1871 Dec 28 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - ANS to the Rev. William Vidler, London, 1846 Nov 11 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 3 ALS to Edward Walford, Exeter and London, 1865 Mar 31-1871 Dec 1 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 3 ALS to Thomas Washorn, London, 1842 Mar 3-1846 Apr 30 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - ALS to an unidentified recipient, London, 1828 Mar 12 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Probably to the editor of the Baptist Magazine. Editor cannot be identified through the 1820 copy of the magazine or through the Baptist bibliographies of Starr and Whitley. Could be the publisher, G. Wightman, but more likely the editor.
  - ANS in French to David [unidentified], [Paris?], 1830 Aug 29 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - ALS in French to an unidentified recipient, Paris, 1834 Apr 8 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Forwarding his report on commercial relations between France and Britain.
  - ALS in French to an unidentified recipient, London, 1835 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 2 ANS and 2 AN in the third person to miscellaneous unidentified recipients, [v.p.], 1842 Jun 12-1870 Aug 23 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Accompanied by Bowring's signature, cut from a letter, and a newspaper clipping.
  - ANS to an unidentified recipient, London, 1860 Apr 27 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Writings, n.d.
  - Autograph manuscript letter concerning commercial relations between France and England, written for publication in The Examiner. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Taxes: autograph manuscript poem in 3 stanzas, signed J. B., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Note: "From the Western Times." Mounted over part of a letter concerning investment in iron mines from an unknown person.
  - Autograph poem, signed at the top, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Tinker 369